Guide to the Richard Hanners manuscript 2020
Montana Historical Society
Richard Hanners manuscript
2020
Montana Historical Society Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-2681 MHSlibrary@mt.gov
MC 460
Hanners, Richard
0.6 linear feet
Collection consists of 2 manuscript volumes written by Richard Hanners. Volumes 1 and 2, entitled "From Superstar to Superfund: The History of a Northwest Montana Aluminum Smelter," detail the history of the Anaconda Company's aluminum smelter on the Flathead River in Columbus Falls, Montana. The manuscript was written in 2020.
Historical Note
Richard Hanners began his manuscript after being hired as an industrial electrician for an aluminum smelter in Columbia Falls, Montana in February 1997. He received a history degree from the University of Montana in 1991. Before moving to Columbia Falls, he worked for a historical research company in Missoula, working primarily with computer databases. Hanners created his own database where he gathered thousands of records on the Columbia Falls aluminum plant for his manuscript.
This manuscript covers the history of aluminum, aluminum production and the aluminum smelter in Columbia Falls. Summary: In 1886, aluminum smelters began cropping up following the discovery of a process (called the Hall-Heroult process) which permitted large scale aluminum production. One of the most prominent aluminum companies in the United States was the Pittsburg Reduction Company, which later changed its name to the Aluminum Company of America, later shortened to Alcoa. By 1930, Alcoa produced and sold nearly 100% of all the aluminum electric transmission cabling in the U.S. By 1941, Alcoa was the only primary aluminum producer in the U.S. After World War II, as the result of a lawsuit, the federal government owned most of the U.S. aluminum industry, thus breaking up the Alcoa monopoly. In 1952, the Anaconda Copper Mining Company (later the Anaconda Company) announced that they would build a new aluminum plant in Columbia Falls, Montana. Fluoride emissions from the smelter polluted the surrounding area, resulting in a lawsuit against the Anaconda Aluminum Company in 1970. By the mid- 1980s, the Anaconda Company’s smelter in Anaconda, along with copper mines in Butte, closed down. In 2009, smelter operations shut down and in 2013 polluted soil around the smelter plant was detected by a EPA contractor. In 2015, Columbia Falls Aluminum Company (formerly the Anaconda Aluminum Company), announced the permanent closure of the aluminum plant in Columbia Falls. The property was placed on the Superfund’s National Priorities List in 2016.
This collection consists of 2 manuscript volumes (66 chapters total) written by Richard Hanners. Volumes 1 (chapters 1-37) and 2 (chapters 38-66), entitled "From Superstar to Superfund: The History of a Northwest Montana Aluminum Smelter," detail the history of the Anaconda Company's aluminum smelter on the Flathead River in Columbus Falls, Montana. Chapters include information on the history of aluminum, the discovery of aluminum metal production, development of aluminum companies, labor organizations, health and safety, aluminum in the World Wars, the involvement of the Anaconda Company, the criminal history of Marc Rich, among other topics. The manuscript was written in 2020.
This collection contains two volumes, arranged in their original order. Each folder contains multiple chapters of the manuscript in numerical order.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Research Center catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Hanners, Richard
Rich, Marc
Aluminum Company of America
Anaconda Company
United States. Bonneville Power Administration
Aluminum
Aluminum plants
Aluminum smelting
Labor Unions -- Montana
World War, 1914-1918
World War, 1939-1945
Anaconda (Mont.)
Columbia Falls (Mont.)
Montana
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Volume 1
  - Foreward, Chapters 1-6, 2020 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Chapters 7-15, 2020 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Chapters 16-25, 2020 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Chapters 26-31, 2020 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Chapters 32-37, 2020 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
- Volume 2
  - Chapters 38-44, 2020 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Chapters 45-52, 2020 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Chapters 53-58, 2020 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - Chapters 59-66, 2020 (Box-folder 2 / 3)